{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man died after having a brain hemorrhage during a conversation with the astronomer\nAnders Johan Lexell [AHN-durrs YOH-hahn LEX-ell] about the recent discovery of Uranus. He\nhad a series of famous arguments about the existence of God with Denis Diderot [deh-nee deedur-oh] in the court of Catherine the Great. His mathematical identity sets e to the i times pi equal to minus 1. For 10 points, name this Swiss mathematician who presented a solution to the Seven\nBridges of Konigsberg [KOHN-eggs-burg] problem.",
      "answer": [
        "Leonhard Euler",
        "Euler"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This Nobel Prize winning-scientist assisted Germany’s production of chlorine gas and oversaw its use at Second Ypres. This Jewish scientist’s lab ironically developed the predecessor to Zyklon B. This is the alphabetically-latter of the two namesakes of a process utilizing Hess’ Law to calculate lattice energies. While working for BASF, Carl Bosch refined a process named for this man. For 10 points, name this developer of the industrial process of ammonia production.",
      "answer": "Fritz Haber"
    },
    {
      "question": "This theory explains the results of an 1851 experiment by Hippolyte Fizeau [EE-poh-leet FEE-zoh]. This theory can be tested by observing decay rates of muons [MEW-ons]. Lorentz transformations are used in this theory, which gives rise to the ladder and twin “paradoxes” thanks to length contraction and time dilation. This theory posits that the speed of light is the same in all reference frames. For 10 points, identify this theory that Albert Einstein proposed a decade before its “general” counterpart.",
      "answer": "special relativity"
    },
    {
      "question": "An effect named for this scientist concerns the rotation of the plane of polarization of light in matter upon the application of magnetic field. His motor used a magnetic field to rotate a current-carrying wire resting on a pool of mercury. An object enclosed by a conductor is unperturbed by external electric fields, and hence rests in a cage named for this man. For 10 points, name this physicist, who started his career as an apprentice to Humphry Davy and discovered a law of electromagnetic induction.",
      "answer": "Michael Faraday"
    },
    {
      "question": "This scientist is often credited with inventing the anchor escapement used in pendulum clocks. Isaac Newton’s quote “If I have seen further it is by standing on the shoulder of giants” was probably a jab at this scientist’s short height. He wrote about his use of microscopes in his book Micrographia, and his namesake law can be stated as restoring force is proportional to displacement. For ten points, name this British scientist who coined the term “cell.”",
      "answer": "Robert Hooke"
    },
    {
      "question": "Thisscientistdiscoveredthatstereoisomersoftartaricacidrotatepolarizedlightinoppositedirections. He saved the silk industry in his country by determining that silkworms were dying from an infectious disease called flacherie. This scientist was able to save Joseph Meister from a dog bite due to his research into a vaccine for rabies. For ten points, name this French scientist whose namesake process removes harmful microorganisms from milk.",
      "answer": "Louis Pasteur"
    },
    {
      "question": "This mathematician names an exact solution to the Einstein field equation describing swirling dust. He spent time in a sanitarium for a nervous breakdown following the murder of Moritz Schlick by Johann Nelbock, who was pardoned after two years by the Nazis. This mathematician is best known for showing that axiomatic systems cannot prove their own consistency and that all axiomatic systems with a notion of arithmetic will contain unprovable truths. For ten points, give this mathematician who names a set of two incompleteness theorems.",
      "answer": "Kurt G¨odel"
    },
    {
      "question": "This scientist disproved Lavoisier’s definition of acids being elements that contain oxygen. This man injured himself while working with nitrogen trichloride, which led to him hiring Michael Faraday as an assistant. This scientist experimented on himself with nitrous oxide, realizing that it could be used as an anesthetic that he nicknamed “laughing gas.” For ten points, name this English scientist who discovered elements like calcium, iodine, and chlorine.",
      "answer": "Sir Humphry Davy"
    },
    {
      "question": "Leo VI the Wise claimed to have invented a hand siphon for use with this material, and dromon galleys had mounted siphons on their prow to launch this weapon. Scientists have doubted phosphine’s potential to be used in this weapon, as its reaction with water isn’t violent enough. Naphtha, quicklime, and sulfur are among the various candidates for the possible ingredients of, for ten points, what seemingly magic incendiary weapon that was used by the Byzantines until knowledge of its production was lost around the 12th century?",
      "answer": "Greek fire"
    },
    {
      "question": "Gerald L. Geison [[GAY-sohn]] showed that this scientist had used deception when reporting his results. This scientist discovered that earthworms could bring diseases to the surface by studying animals dying in \"cursed fields.\" This scientist applied his findings from studying chicken cholera to create the first anthrax vaccine. This scientist dried out infected nerve tissue from rabbits to create the world's first rabies vaccine. For ten points, name this French biologist who names the process of heating milk to kill microorganisms.",
      "answer": "Louis Pasteur 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8"
    },
    {
      "question": "One member of this family promoted the terrible singing of his wife, Ganna Walska [[HAWN-ah WAHL-skah]], which Orson Welles claimed inspired the screenplay of Citizen Kane. The Brazilian embassy in the U.S. is housed in a manor once owned by this family. One member of this family invented a device he called a \"hemp-break.\" This family owned the Chicago Tribune for much of the 20th century, and a member of this family invented the mechanical reaper. For ten points, name this family which merged its company with Deering to form International Harvester.",
      "answer": [
        "McCormick",
        "Harold McCormick",
        "Robert McCormick, Jr. 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 9"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Auguste Mariette led an effort to clear this monument of debris prior to a visit by the Emperor of Brazil, Pedro II. Historians discovered that several 18th dynasty rulers may have suffered from familial epilepsy due to the Dream Stele [[STEE-lee]] situated in front of this monument. A now debunked theory claimed this monument lost its nose to cannon fire from Napoleon's army during the Battle of the Pyramids. The Pharaoh Khafre is depicted with the body of a lion in, for ten points, which monumental statue in Giza?",
      "answer": "Great Sphinx of Giza"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was deemed a \"White Jew\" in an editorial in Das Schwarze Korps, the SS newspaper, after he was named \"favorite\" to head the Munich Faculty. With a set of scientists, including Walther Gerlach, this physicist was detained in England through Operation Epsilon to determine how close the Nazis were to creating an atomic bomb. Albert Einstein nominated this scientist for a 1932 Nobel Prize in Physics he won for determining limits to predicting physical quantities of particles. An \"Uncertainty Principle\" is named for, for ten points, which \"Father of Quantum Mechanics\"?",
      "answer": [
        "Werner Heisenberg or Werner Karl Heisenberg",
        "Heisenberg Uncertainty Principle"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man’s body was allegedly placed in a glass coffin, but a team of forensic scientists discovered it was incorrectly identified. After this man executed the loser of the Battle of Cajamarca [[kah-hah-MAHR-kah]], this man had two sons with his widow, renamed Dona Angelina. This man’s life ended when supporters of Diego de Almagro's son stormed a palace and assassinated him, making Almagro the new Governor of Peru. For ten points, name this conquistador who founded Lima after destroying the Inca Empire.",
      "answer": "Francisco Pizarro or Francisco Pizarro González"
    },
    {
      "question": "Author Ken Kesey unknowingly took part in these experiments at the Veterans Administration Hospital in Menlo Park while working there as a night aide. One revelation from hearings on this project was that Frank Olson, a U.S. Army biochemist, died from being covertly dosed by an experimental drug under the auspices of this program. Originally designed to test the effects of psychoactive drugs on eliciting confessions during interrogations, for ten points, give the codename for what series of illegal and highly- secretive human experiments conducted by the CIA?",
      "answer": "Project MKUltra"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scientist invented the parallel linkage, found in some automobile axles. This scientist, along with his business partners Matthew Boulton and James Keir, developed a machine to copy ink documents. This scientist’s separation of the condenser and cylinder in a previous invention developed by Thomas Newcomen allowed it to become the most widely used power source during the Industrial Revolution. For ten points, name this inventor of a rotary steam engine and the namesake of the SI unit for power.",
        "answer": "James Watt"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "James Watt coined this unit of measure, equal to about 750 Watts, as a relation to the power output of manually spinning mill wheels.",
        "answer": "horsepower"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scientist went to work at the Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions after he was forced to step down from his position at Caltech due to his antiwar positions. This man proposed an incorrect triple helix model for DNA and recommended treating the common cold and cancer with high dosages of Vitamin C. This scientist also introduced orbital hybridization and the electronegativity scale. For ten points, name this two time Nobel laureate.",
        "answer": "Linus Pauling"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Pauling and colleagues determined that a defect in hemoglobin is the cause of this disease. The fact that it makes its victims immune to malaria was first observed in African slaves taken to the Americas.",
        "answer": "sickle cell anemia"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A type of this disease that makes surgery difficult was discovered by Henry Pancoast. Fritz Lickint experimented with X-raying the spleen as a cure for this disease and coined the term for a “passive” cause of it. Scientists in Nazi Germany discovered the link between this disease and asbestos. In the late 1990s, Philip Morris admitted that its products cause this disease. For ten points, name this type of cancer often caused by smoking tobacco.",
        "answer": "lung cancer"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This term for smoke inhaled by non-smokers developed out of Fritz Lickint’s theories about the dangers of “passive smoking.” Governments have cited the dangers of this type of environmental exposure to smoke when passing laws banning smoking in public.",
        "answer": [
          "second-hand smoke",
          "word forms"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This invention is believed to have been first created by the Swedish army officer D.H. Fridberg, who produced the “Kjellman” [k’yell-man] version. Later versions of this device were manufactured by Hotchkiss and Vickers. Hiram Maxim perfected the first practical form of this weapon, which was used to sustained, deadly effect in No Man’s Land during World War I. John Browning also designed, for ten points, what fully automatic weapons that often use a belt feeder and a bipod stand?",
        "answer": "machine gun"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During World War I, this German airplane manufacturer invented the gun synchronizer to prevent machine guns mounted on fighters from firing bullets into the propellers.",
        "answer": [
          "Fokker Aviatik GmBH",
          "Fokker Flugzeugwerke GmbH",
          "Fokker Werke GmbH",
          "Fokker Aeroplanbau"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This project was spurred on by a 1986 conference led by Charles DeLisi in Santa Fe. The Celera Corporation, founded by Craig Venter, competed with this project using a “shotgun” technique and saw its stock price crash after President Clinton announced patents on this project’s findings would not be granted. Francis Collins and James Watson were leaders of, for ten points, what project, the world’s largest collaborative biological research project, that created a mosaic-like mapping of the sequence of human DNA in the 1990s?",
        "answer": "Human Genome Project or HGP"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This scientist invented a namesake type of sequencing that was initially used by the Human Genome Project, for which he received his second Nobel Prize in Chemistry. This man also determined the primary structure of insulin.",
        "answer": "Frederick Sanger"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a work partially named for this figure, Minerva points to a printing press near famed inventors and Liberty holds a fasces and wears a Phrygian cap. This figure leans on his horse at Verplanck’s Point in New York in a John Trumbull work that was followed by a similar pose of this man in front of Evacuation Day proceedings. The government commissioned Constantino Brumidi to paint the Apotheosis of this leader for the US Capitol rotunda. For ten points, name this man whose portrait was saved by Dolley Madison during the burning of D.C. in 1814.",
        "answer": "George Washington"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the inventors near Minerva in The Apotheosis of Washington was this man, who built the first practical submarine for Napoleon and the Clermont, the first commercially successful steamboat.",
        "answer": "Robert Fulton"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scientist's home was the Down House, whose grounds contain a \"sandwalk\" which this scientist called his \"thinking path.\" On one journey to South America, this scientist wrote that a native species of fox \"would undermine the stability of species.\" This scientist's observations of tortoises helped him formulate his idea that species change over time. This scientist recorded his travels in the book The Voyage of the Beagle. For ten points, name this English scientist, who outlined his theory of natural selection in On the Origin of Species.",
        "answer": "Charles Darwin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "English biologist Thomas Huxley became known by the canine nickname \"Darwin's [this animal]\" following a famous debate with William Wilberforce on the factuality of evolution.",
        "answer": "Bulldog 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 3"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This scientist's views were criticized in the Blockhead and Chinese Room thought experiments. This scientist may have committed suicide by injecting cyanide into an apple. This scientist names a 2017 law that retroactively pardons British men convicted of homosexuality. This scientist's namesake machine is an idealized computer which reads symbols from an infinite tape. For ten points, name this computer scientist who names a test that distinguishes between humans and machines.",
        "answer": "Alan Turing"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During World War Two, Alan Turing developed a machine that could find settings for this previously unbreakable Nazi cipher device.",
        "answer": "Enigma machine 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 9"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While serving as a captain in the German army, Otto Jaekal [[YEH-kul]] excavated for these animals in the mines of the occupied Belgian town of Bernissart. The rivalry between American scientists Edward Drinker Cope and Othniel Charles Marsh led to the \"Bone Wars,\" a period of discovery of this general class of animals. The ancient Chinese believed to have found \"dragon bones\" after discovering the remains of, for ten points, what general class of reptiles which include T. Rex?",
        "answer": [
          "Dinosaurs",
          "Dinosaur fossils"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Marsh earned the right to excavate for dinosaur fossils in which native tribe's Black Hills by negotiating with Chief Red Cloud?",
        "answer": [
          "Sioux",
          "Lakota",
          "or Oglala Lakota",
          "or Dakota",
          "Očhéthi Šakówiŋ",
          "or Seven Council Fires"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Renaissance",
      "prompt": "During the Renaissance...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Who diagrammed anatomy in Vitruvian Man and painted the Mona Lisa?",
          "answer": [
            "Leonardo da Vinci",
            "either"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Who used his telescopes to discover moons of Jupiter, including Io?",
          "answer": [
            "Galileo Galilei",
            "either"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "What city, the birthplace of that astronomer, built a bell tower on less-than-solid ground?",
          "answer": "Pisa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Who invented a movable-type printing press to enable mass communication?",
          "answer": "Johannes Gutenberg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which ruling family of Florence supported the arts and produced four popes?",
          "answer": "Medici"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which “father of empiricism” advanced the scientific method in works like Novum Organum?",
          "answer": "Francis Bacon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which Dutch humanist wrote In Praise of Folly?",
          "answer": "Desiderius Erasmus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Which English architect designed Banqueting House, Whitehall and Queen’s House, Greenwich?",
          "answer": "Inigo Jones"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Famous Canadians",
      "prompt": "Which Canadian...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Has hosted Jeopardy! for over 30 years?",
          "answer": "Alex Trebek"
        },
        {
          "question": "Invented numerous hearing aid devices, as well as the telephone?",
          "answer": "Alexander Graham Bell"
        },
        {
          "question": "Took a “long walk in the snow” in 1984, after which he announced plans to retire as Prime Minister?",
          "answer": "Pierre Trudeau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Invented basketball at a YMCA in Springfield, Massachusetts?",
          "answer": "James Naismith"
        },
        {
          "question": "Discussed wealth discrepancies in post-World War II America in The Affluent Society?",
          "answer": "John Kenneth Galbraith"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wrote “In Flanders Fields” in memory of a fallen friend during World War I?",
          "answer": "John McCrae"
        },
        {
          "question": "Won a Nobel at age 32 for his discovery of insulin?",
          "answer": "Frederick Banting"
        },
        {
          "question": "Commanded the ISS in 2013 and became the first Canadian to walk in space?",
          "answer": "Chris Hadfield"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Brahmagupta sometimes lends his name to this mathematician’s identity writing a product of sums of squares itself as a sum of squares. This man’s most famous book was among the first to use Arabic numerals. (20 pts)",
        "Binet’s [bih-nays] formula gives values of a sequence named after this man, and the ratio between those values approximates the (10 pts)",
        "golden ratio. This mathematician developed his most famous result by considering the monthly reproduction of rabbits. For 10 points, identify this mathematician whose book Liber Abaci introduced a sequence beginning 1,1,2,3,5."
      ],
      "answer": "Leonardo Fibonacci"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This scientist postulated that the deficiency in color perception among the color-blind is due to a discoloration of the liquid medium of the eyeball. This man was the first to show that the (20 pts)",
        "pressure of a mixture of gases is equal to the sum of its components’ partial pressures. A mass unit named for this man is equal to (10 pts)",
        "one-twelfth the weight of a neutral atom of carbon, exactly one amu. For 10 points, name this English chemist who developed the law of multiple proportions, a component of his modern atomic theory."
      ],
      "answer": "John Dalton"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man examined the long-term effects of military socialization on soldiers in his recently developed \"social intensity syndrome.\" This man attempted to explain how good people have the capacity to do evil in his book The (20 pts)",
        "Lucifer Effect. A 1971 experiment conducted by this man was funded by the US Office of Naval Research and included the exceptionally brutal (10 pts)",
        "\"John Wayne.\" That experiment placed a divided group of students in a simulated jail for 6 days. For 10 points, name this psychologist who conducted the Stanford Prison Experiment."
      ],
      "answer": "Philip Zimbardo"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Charles II excused this scientist from having to become an ordained priest after he became a fellow of Trinity College. This scientist, whose ideas on the scientific method included his statement of “Hypotheses non fingo,” attributed his own success to “standing on the (20 pts)",
        "shoulders of giants.” This scientist retreated to his family home during an outbreak of plague in Cambridge, then developed a theory of (10 pts)",
        "optics and an inverse square law describing forces between any two objects. For ten points, name this scientist who developed three laws of motion and a law of universal gravitation."
      ],
      "answer": "Sir Isaac Newton"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This scientist’s Ostomachion is a tangram-like puzzle with 14 pieces. His geometric accomplishments include relating the volumes of a cylinder and sphere with equal radius and using a method of exhaustion to estimate 22/7 as an upper bound for (20 pts)",
        "pi. His military inventions include a mechanical claw to lift ships out of the water and a (10 pts)",
        "“death ray” designed using parabolic mirrors to try to burn incoming ships, meant to protect his home city during the Punic wars. A device that lifts liquids through rotation is a screw named for, for ten points, what Syracuse mathematician?"
      ],
      "answer": "Archimedes"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The occurrence of one of these events during a battle between the Medes and the Lydians caused both sides to put down their weapons and declare peace. Certain predictions from Einstein’s theory of (20 pts)",
        "general relativity were confirmed following Arthur Eddington’s observation of light deflection during one of these events in 1919. Historians have attempted to place the exact date of Good Friday by assuming that the (10 pts)",
        "darkness described at Jesus’ crucifixion was one of these events. For ten points, name these events in which the moon passes between the Sun and the Earth."
      ],
      "answer": "solar eclipse"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This scientist worked with Pierre-Simon Laplace on a work read to the Royal Academy of Sciences, Memoir on Heat. He discovered that respiration is a form of combustion and that diamonds are composed of carbon. Works by this chemist include his (20 pts)",
        "Essays Physical and Chemical and his Elementary Treatise on Chemistry. This chemist named oxygen and hydrogen and disproved the phlogiston theory; he also developed the law of conservation of mass before (10 pts)",
        "losing his head to the guillotine. For ten points, name this French scientist, often considered the father of modern chemistry."
      ],
      "answer": "Antoine Lavoisier"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This scientist’s namesake constant is equal to the time derivative of the scale factor over the scale factor, and the reciprocal of that constant is equal to the age of the Universe. This man’s namesake (20 pts)",
        "law, which was discovered while working at the Mount Wilson Observatory, states that the recessional velocity of a galaxy is proportional to its distance from us; that implies the occurrence of the Big Bang. The “Pillars of Creation” (10 pts)",
        "photograph was taken by a device named for, for ten points, what American astronomer who names a space telescope launched in 1990?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Edwin Hubble",
        "Hubble constant, Hubble’s Law, and/or Hubble Space Telescope"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man analyzed whether watching a specially-curated episode of the show Medical Center would trigger anti-social behavior in participants. A mind-body thought experiment by this thinker imagines a human being serving as an interlocutor for another’s thoughts; this thinker called those beings (20 pts)",
        "“cyranoids.” The trial of Adolf Eichmann inspired another one of this thinker’s experiments, some variants of which were conducted at a nearby warehouse rather than at a (10 pts)",
        "Yale laboratory. For ten points, name this social psychologist who encouraged unknowing participants to administer shocks under the orders of an authority figure."
      ],
      "answer": "Stanley Milgram"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) For designing one of these facilities, John Cockcroft and Ernest Walton won a Nobel Prize in 1951. After already spending 2 billion dollars, the development of one of these facilities named the SSC was canceled by (20 pts)",
        "Congress in 1993. Public safety concerns were raised after people thought one of these facilities built by CERN was capable of producing black (10 pts)",
        "holes. The Tevatron and the RHIC are examples of, for ten points, what scientific devices used to study physics at the atomic level, such as the Large Hadron Collider?"
      ],
      "answer": "particle accelerators"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A device that relies on this effect called an h/e apparatus can be used to experimentally determine Planck’s constant. This effect was discovered after an observation that illumination with UV light made electrodes produce (20 pts)",
        "sparks more easily. As the theories of relativity were still controversial in 1921, the Nobel committee emphasized the discovery of this effect in (10 pts)",
        "Albert Einstein’s citation. For ten points, name this effect in which high-energy photons dislodge electrons from a metal."
      ],
      "answer": "photoelectric effect"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man called the rapid spread of angiosperms during the Cretaceous Period an “abominable mystery” in a letter to the director of the Kew Gardens, Joseph Hooker. Upon receiving a plant from Madagascar, this man predicted the existence of a pollinator moth that (20 pts)",
        "evolved along with it in his Fertilization of Orchids. Syms Covington and Robert FitzRoy helped this man collect specimens that (10 pts)",
        "ornithologist John Gould later determined to be separate species of Galapagos finches. The theory of natural selection was pioneered by, for ten points, what author of On the Origin of Species?"
      ],
      "answer": "Charles Darwin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man, who reverse-engineered the manufacture of Nuremburg Bronze Powder and patented a method for making a ribbon of plate glass, offered James Nasmyth a one-third share in his most famous invention. William Kelly also experimented with this man’s primary discovery, whose use drove the growth of Sheffield in England. (20 pts)",
        "Gilchrist and Thomas modified this man’s work for use on high phosphorus material, and the open hearth (10 pts)",
        "furnace rendered this man’s work largely obsolete. For ten points, name this English inventor of a method for blowing air into molten pig iron, a revolution in modern steelmaking."
      ],
      "answer": "Henry Bessemer"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Early scientists who isolated this molecule included Friedrich Miescher [[MEE- shuh]] and Albrecht Kossel. Despite producing \"Photo 51\" that contributed to the discovery of this molecule's structure, Rosalind (20 pts)",
        "Franklin did not receive a Nobel Prize for her work. Okazaki fragments of this molecule are pieced together by a namesake ligase [[LAI-gase]], and this molecule is unwound by a namesake (10 pts)",
        "helicase [[HEE-lih-case]]. James Watson and Francis Crick discovered the double-helix structure of, for ten points, what molecule which contains genetic information?"
      ],
      "answer": "DNA or Deoxyribonucleic acid"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) This scientist disputed Christoph Scheiner's claims in the Apelles letters by claiming his observations took place first in the Letters on Sunspots. This man may have depicted (+) Pope Urban VIII as the dimwitted \"Simplicio\" in his Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems, and was widely held to have muttered \"And yet it (*) moves\" after publicly recanting his theories. For ten points, name this Italian scientist who was found guilty of heresy for promoting heliocentrism.",
      "answer": [
        "G",
        "a",
        "l",
        "i",
        "e",
        "o",
        "r",
        "d",
        "V",
        "n",
        "c",
        "z",
        "B",
        "u",
        "t",
        "'",
        ";",
        "p",
        "h"
      ]
    }
  ]
}